<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog</id>
    <title>Jake Nichols UI Portfolio Blog</title>
    <updated>2024-09-25T18:50:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Jake Nichols UI Portfolio Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Did I Choose Purple For My Portfolio?]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-2</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-2"/>
        <updated>2024-09-25T18:50:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following blog post explains my reasoning based on Eiseman's The Complete Color Harmony for choosing purple as the primary color of this portfolio.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following blog post explains my reasoning based on Eiseman's <em>The Complete Color Harmony<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-2#user-content-fn-1-ccc164" id="user-content-fnref-1-ccc164" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em> for choosing purple as the primary color of this portfolio.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/purple-be7f6d2de53bf8057d7b122c004b7674.jpeg" title="A sunset over a purple sky" width="5000" height="3333" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">In the Simplest Terms: Purple is Stunning</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;While I won't deny that purple being my favorite color plays a large role in the decision to use it here,
there are further reasons why I think it's a good choice for a UI (though to some degree, I'm justifying this for the same reasons it's my favorite color).</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;I find purple unique in the sense that you don't see it used often in more professional settings. It's often relegated to its connotations of royalty, mystique,
or flamboyancy, but I personally agree with the sentiment that purples on the blue end of the spectrum can appear very elegant &amp; dignified. It's eye-catching
but in a subtler sense than a bright orange or deep red. Purple makes a statement without screaming at you to listen.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Speaking to those who choose to listen is how I like to view my own approach to conversation. I don't take my place in a conversation
by being the loudest but simply by having something to say. Sometimes this may get drowned out by louder voices such as the oranges &amp; reds of the world, but
the reserved thoughts are there for those who choose to listen. Perhaps this has nothing to do with purple, and I'm just projecting my personality onto
my favorite color. Perhaps my personality lead me to choose a color I identify with.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Or, perhaps purple has influenced my personality... much like the personality of this portfolio.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-2#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-ccc164">
<p>Eiseman, Leatrice. The Complete Color Harmony: Expert Color Information for Professional Results. Rockport Publishers, an Imprint of The Quarto Group, 2017. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-2#user-content-fnref-1-ccc164" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="FreeForm" term="FreeForm"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Color is to Design as Spice is to Cooking]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-1</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-1"/>
        <updated>2024-09-23T16:23:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following post reflects on Eiseman's The Complete Color Harmony as it relates to color theory and the role of color in design as compared to spice in cooking.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following post reflects on Eiseman's <em>The Complete Color Harmony<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-1#user-content-fn-1-6bf4cc" id="user-content-fnref-1-6bf4cc" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em> as it relates to color theory and the role of color in design as compared to spice in cooking.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/spice-2ab3b9d8248ecff59fc2f880fe7ef236.jpeg" title="Various colorful spices in bowls" width="5849" height="3910" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Spice Itself Comes in Many Colors</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;In the same sense that no dish is complete without spice, no interface is complete without color. Sure, some people cook with
little more than salt in the same way that some websites use simple black text on white backgrounds. Though there may be a time and place for this type of
design (Wikipedia comes to mind, but even they use some amount of color), most interfaces would be horribly boring without a good color scheme. In the same
way, salt may be all you need when cooking for picky eaters or just making something edible, but the dish will never reach the same heights it would with
a full flavor profile of spices.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Color doesn't often define an interface, but it's an almost necessary component to create something that will stick with users
after they stop interacting with your interface due to the emotional significance of color. Like spice, it's also important to pick the correct color combinations.
Throwing everything &amp; the kitchen sink into a dish or design is a good way to overwhelm users and create something with no identity. Color palettes are often created
from three colors which play off of each other in one way or another just like a recipe often calls for a handful of complementary spices.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Color's importance and necessitation of both restraint and combination are important to remember for anyone going into UI design
or really any career that relates to interfaces. Without understanding these concepts, you're bound to go too far to one end of the spectrum. Understanding
how to use smart color combinations and experiment to create your own unique themes will elevate everything from new UIs to simple updates of existing ones.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-1#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-6bf4cc">
<p>Eiseman, Leatrice. The Complete Color Harmony: Expert Color Information for Professional Results. Rockport Publishers, an Imprint of The Quarto Group, 2017. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-1#user-content-fnref-1-6bf4cc" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="ApproximateAnalogy" term="ApproximateAnalogy"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aesthetic Design - How to Design Effective Slides]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/aesthetic-design</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/aesthetic-design"/>
        <updated>2024-09-18T19:49:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following tutorial contains key points & reminders from Presentation Zen on how to create attention-grabbing/effective PowerPoint slides.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following tutorial contains key points &amp; reminders from <em>Presentation Zen<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/aesthetic-design#user-content-fn-1-ec306f" id="user-content-fnref-1-ec306f" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em> on how to create attention-grabbing/effective PowerPoint slides.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/presentation_stock-b8059233ce7b2e3dabee2892be754d00.jpeg" title="Example presentations with good formatting" width="5477" height="2739" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">An Example of Simple But Effective Slides</p><p></p>
<p>Avoid Bullet-Points (mostly)</p>
<ul>
<li>Bullet-points are often used as a crutch in slide design with most of the words to be spoken, but they should be used sparingly.</li>
<li>You can get away with including much less of what you're going to say on the slides, or you can break up lists into multiple slides with one or two key points each.</li>
</ul>
<p>Pay Attention to Eyes</p>
<ul>
<li>When including images of people or animals, make sure the eyes don't lead users away from slide content.</li>
<li>Try to use images where the eyes point at your content, and flip/rearrange images that don't.</li>
</ul>
<p>Break Up Large Quotes (if necessary)</p>
<ul>
<li>Longer quotes can be easier to read in chunks instead of a one large block.</li>
<li>If doing this, break it down into distinct sections on different slides &amp; focus in on the significance of each one.</li>
</ul>
<p>Eliminate Noise Around Charts</p>
<ul>
<li>Make sure background colors &amp; images don't conflict with the viewer's ability to read a read any elements of charts.</li>
<li>Select simple graph layouts (2D is almost always better than 3D).</li>
<li>Choose colors for graph elements that work well together &amp; don't distract from information.</li>
</ul>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/aesthetic-design#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-ec306f">
<p>Reynolds, Garr. Presentation Zen: Simple Ideas on Presentation Design and Delivery. Pearson Education, 2019. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/aesthetic-design#user-content-fnref-1-ec306f" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="Tutorial" term="Tutorial"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Analysis of Shneiderman - The Eyes Have It]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/shneiderman-analysis</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/shneiderman-analysis"/>
        <updated>2024-09-06T15:06:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is a meta reflection on Ben Shneiderman's paper, "The Eyes Have It: A Task by Data Type Taxonomy for Information Visualizations" as well as a reflection on the importance of this paper's concepts in the industry.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is a meta reflection on Ben Shneiderman's paper, "The Eyes Have It: A Task by Data Type Taxonomy for Information Visualizations"<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/shneiderman-analysis#user-content-fn-1-5da721" id="user-content-fnref-1-5da721" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup> as well as a reflection on the importance of this paper's concepts in the industry.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/tunnel_vision-565df1a7f50d952add711ac357c6eac8.jpeg" title="Tunnel vision" width="5856" height="3904" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Artistic Depiction of Tunnel Vision</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;I found a lot of this paper to be bogged down in implementation details of specific problems/solutions which I don't find terribly helpful when trying to learn a concept.
It's okay to provide examples, but the section on "Overview" for example felt overly-specific. I don't see as much value in talking about specific zoom factors and field-of-view boxes when introducing a concept in a paper like this.
I would've preferred more high-level explanation &amp; justification for the techniques personally.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;As far as career importance, the meta point would be to avoid getting caught up in implementation details when having conversations with non-technical stakeholders (or even technical stakeholders in certain cases).
In terms of the actual content of the reading, the principles themselves that were outlined are important to keep in mind while building a UI as they're good guidelines &amp; standards for guiding a user's interaction with your interface.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/shneiderman-analysis#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-5da721">
<p>B. Shneiderman, "The eyes have it: a task by data type taxonomy for information visualizations," Proceedings 1996 IEEE Symposium on Visual Languages, Boulder, CO, USA, 1996, pp. 336-343, doi: 10.1109/VL.1996.545307. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/shneiderman-analysis#user-content-fnref-1-5da721" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
</feed>