<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog</id>
    <title>Jake Nichols UI Portfolio Blog</title>
    <updated>2024-11-24T19:04:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Jake Nichols UI Portfolio Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[UIUN Reflection]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/uiun</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/uiun"/>
        <updated>2024-11-24T19:04:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is a reflection of a workshop/activity held at my college which was called the UIUN Summit.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is a reflection of a workshop/activity held at my college which was called the UIUN Summit.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/language-48f98f0600b5bd7a5a234af87268ce18.jpeg" title="An image of hands holding up the word &amp;quot;hello&amp;quot; in various languages" width="6138" height="2444" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Recently, I participated in an activity referred to as the UIUN Summit. This was designed
to be a bit of a workshop that was meant to induce negotiations between students about the accessibility needs of certain
populations in a mock redesign of a government website. Each student chose a population for which designers need to meet
certain accessibility standards to properly accommodate. The name UIUN comes from the activity being modeled after a United
Nations meeting in which individuals represent the needs of their country. As someone who originally intended to minor in
Spanish in college, I decided to represent the non-native English-speaking/English as a Second Language (ESL) population.
We first gave brief introductions to our population based on initial research. We then designed presentations covering our
population's needs in-depth, and finally, we held negotiations over the most important requirements to make it into a
redesigned local election site.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Off the bat, I had assumed that vocabulary would be the biggest hurdle for my population.
Having taken four years of Spanish, I was generally able to parse the meaning of a sentence with enough time even if I
didn't fully understand the grammar, but vocab isn't something you can really intuit unless words are conjugates or there
are enough context clues. Upon further research, this was supported by an article from Bay Atlantic University over the
challenges ESL students face in the classroom.<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/uiun#user-content-fn-1-6559ab" id="user-content-fnref-1-6559ab" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup> Unfortunately, this was one of the only strong pieces of research I was able to
find on my population. While there are lots of guidelines and standards for inclusive design regarding populations who
depend on screen readers for example, ESL doesn't have the same standards when designing with accessibility in mind.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;For the research of my presentation, I essentially just had to extrapolate from the needs of
ESL students in the classroom as well as from Census data. Though not ideal, I was able to come up with another major need
of non-native English speakers which is clear FAQ and instructions to prevent the need to speak to a live representative.
Speaking and listening were the hardest skills in my Spanish journey, and my research backed up that one of the biggest
struggles for ESL students is finding confidence and motivation to engage with others in English.<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/uiun#user-content-fn-1-6559ab" id="user-content-fnref-1-6559ab-2" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup> I focused my
requirements around these two points. Additionally, anything that makes the text itself more difficult to parse is an added
barrier to any population, especially those who have trouble comprehending meaning. For this reason, I included a requirement
regarding clear and adjustable fonts. You can read the three requirements for my population in full here:</p>
<ul>
<li>Flesch-Kincade testing should be used as a sanity check on all pages to ensure that writing is kept to a reasonable level such as 7th - 8th grade.</li>
<li>All necessary information to vote should be available and clear online to prevent the need to speak to an English-speaking representative.</li>
<li>Adjustable fonts should be available to minimize struggles that aren't related to comprehension.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;After presentations concluded, we met as a group and tried to list, rank, and choose the roughly 4-5
most important requirements which could gain support from multiple populations. Unfortunately, I found this to be the weakest
aspect of the activity. I think we had a pretty non-confrontational group who wasn't interested in having heated discussions over
an activity such as this (including myself). For the most part, one person lead the discussions. I don't know that anyone fought
too hard over what they wanted, and we didn't really mark anything that wasn't unanimous or at least that everyone felt indifferent
about. Towards the end, I tried to push the 7th - 8th grade writing level requirement as it had a lot of support from other groups,
but I felt this was mostly shut down on pedantic reasons such as the wording of the requirement as it was listed in our ranking
rather than the requirement itself.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;By the end of negotiations, our requirements became a lot messier as it was suggested by the moderator
that we could pack multiple issues into one "bill" much like the worst aspect of the American political system which prevents nearly
all bipartisan initiatives from passing in Congress, but I digress. Requirements started having unrelated things tacked on in an
attempt to satisfy more populations. I don't think this was realistic to the amount of effort necessary to complete each requirement
that got packed together as we were supposed to have a limited budget on priorities. Overall, this derailed the negotation aspect and
diminished the quality of the exercise in my opinion.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;One thing that surprised me about negotiations was the amount of overlap my requirements had with
the population of people with Dyslexia. In hindsight, this makes sense as both populations primarily struggle with language and
comprehension. Additionally, children under 13 were a strong ally, but I did predict this since children are also generally at
a point where they are still learning English and how to fully comprehend it. We also unfortunately didn't have a representative
present for a population reliant on screen readers. However, one student chose to play that part briefly which threw a wrench
in things. Though in a real project, you would absolutely develop for screen readers from the start, we had neglected this until
the end and basically had to convince them that we couldn't afford that anymore. Feeling forced to deny a major requirement for
such a large portion of web users wasn't a great feeling. However, I think this came down more to the structure of the activity
and the order in which we proceeded rather than a realistic representation of design.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Ultimately, the summit was an interesting (albeit flawed) exercise in inclusive design. While it got
me thinking more about the importance of designing for populations with accessibility needs, I think it would've been more productive
without some of the strange constraints around the negotiations and a more involved group. If there's one takeaway I can pull from this,
it's that if put in a situation like this in industry, I realize now that you have to fight for a population's needs if you want them
to make it into an already packed backlog.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/uiun#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-6559ab">
<p>Bay Atlantic University "ESL Students Challenges: Overcoming Language Obstacles." Bay Atlantic University - Washington, D.C., 15 Mar. 2024, bau.edu/blog/esl-students-challenges/. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/uiun#user-content-fnref-1-6559ab" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a> <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/uiun#user-content-fnref-1-6559ab-2" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1-2" class="data-footnote-backref">↩<sup>2</sup></a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="FreeForm" term="FreeForm"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clarity in Constraints]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/constraints</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/constraints"/>
        <updated>2024-10-31T17:59:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is a reflection of chapter 4 of Don Norman's The Design of Everyday Things.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is a reflection of chapter 4 of Don Norman's <em>The Design of Everyday Things.<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/constraints#user-content-fn-1-706c81" id="user-content-fnref-1-706c81" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/confusion-adfb8bf25e562534172da34e7cc0bb9f.jpeg" title="Confusion stock image" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Never lead your users in opposing directions</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Clarity</strong> is an extremely important aspect of any part of design. In particular, constraints need
to be clear such that users won't interpret what they're allowed to do in wildly different ways. Cultural constraints in particular
can be grounds for lots of confusion. For this reason, UIs should aim to use globally-recognizable standards when inducing constraints or at
least specify the standard which they're expecting.
It may feel tempting to design specifically for users of the country you live in because that is the first market you want to capture.
However, this is bound to lead to confusion down the line if your application grows into something bigger.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;One obvious example of a poor cultural constraint is designing an application such that it expects weight
in pounds without clarifying this to the user. While US users will mostly follow this constraint implicitly, nearly any other country
will give you data that you won't be handling correctly. Though we don't have a universal unit to use in a situation like this, specifying
the expected input format or allowing your users to select a unit preference is a simple solution to prevent ambiguity across cultures.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;At the company I work for, we have an entire department dedicated to addressing cultural constraints and
differences. While this isn't necessary for every team, putting a little forethought into the cultural constraints of your application
is a surefire way to prevent unplanned for issues in a growing application.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/constraints#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-706c81">
<p>Norman, Don. The Design of Everyday Things. Basic Books, 2013. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/constraints#user-content-fnref-1-706c81" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Remembering Everyone in Accessibility]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/accessbility-1</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/accessbility-1"/>
        <updated>2024-10-31T17:01:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is a reflection of chapter 12 of Steve Krug's Don't Make Me Think.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is a reflection of chapter 12 of Steve Krug's <em>Don't Make Me Think.<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/accessbility-1#user-content-fn-1-611149" id="user-content-fnref-1-611149" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/accessibility-e21b25cde464412744bd031f0d8be13e.jpeg" title="Accessibility stock image" width="5477" height="2739" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Accessibility features help everyone</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Everyone</strong> is the key word to remember when it comes to developing
accessibility features. While the first intinct for most of us when asked to think of who will benefit from
accessibility improvements is to imagine some stereotype of a person with a disability, anyone can benefit
form these features.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Krug mentions that many resources use the tired example of closed captioning benefiting most
people, but this can be applied in so many other ways. As someone with ever-deteriorating eyesight (i.e. a human),
I find myself squinting more and more at small and even regular text sizes. Customizable font sizes go a long way in
improving a site's accessibility for everyone.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Another great accessibility feature comes from colorblind filters. While this is a little less of a serious example,
a lot of colorblind features allow users who don't experience colorblindness to customize their experience. One way I see this used is in video
games where users will use certain colorblind filters to alter the appearance of an effect to their liking or perhaps make the game less aggressive to
their eyes.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Regardless who your main user base is, accessiblity options are always important to keep in mind as a developer
since they can benefit everyone in ways you may never expect.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/accessbility-1#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-611149">
<p>Krug, Steve. Don't Make Me Think: Revisited. A Common Sense Approach to Web and Mobile Usability. New Riders, 2014. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/accessbility-1#user-content-fnref-1-611149" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prioritizing Fixes From User Tests]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/debriefing-user-tests</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/debriefing-user-tests"/>
        <updated>2024-10-24T17:54:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is a reflection of chapters 8 & 9 of Steve Krug's Don't Make Me Think.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is a reflection of chapters 8 &amp; 9 of Steve Krug's <em>Don't Make Me Think.<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/debriefing-user-tests#user-content-fn-1-57bba3" id="user-content-fnref-1-57bba3" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/priority-54d8ebd79b8fd0fed25f72bdf4d4a030.jpeg" title="High priority stock image" width="5000" height="3333" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Focus on the priorities</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Prioritization</strong> is the main point I took away from Krug's thoughts
on how to debrief after a user test. It's important to narrow down the changes you intend to make based on feedback
to only the most important points. If you try to fix everything, you'll end up changing things which aren't truly
problems and just grievances of a particular user. Knowing how to identify the difference is key in prioritizing
the proper issues. In Krug's methodology, it's important to work with your team (assuming you have one) to debate
and collectively set the top priorities. This also allows others to stop you if you get too wrapped up in something
that doesn't really need a fix.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Prioritization is a useful skill as a developer since you can often get caught up in
what you want to do rather than what's most beneficial to the project. Though some amount of this is the burden of
a project manager, it's still important to understand your priorities and to use your own judgement in tackling the
issues with the highest return on investment.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/debriefing-user-tests#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-57bba3">
<p>Krug, Steve. Don't Make Me Think: Revisited. A Common Sense Approach to Web and Mobile Usability. New Riders, 2014. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/debriefing-user-tests#user-content-fnref-1-57bba3" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Giving Space in User Tests]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/user-tests</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/user-tests"/>
        <updated>2024-10-24T17:54:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is a reflection of chapters 8 & 9 of Steve Krug's Don't Make Me Think.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is a reflection of chapters 8 &amp; 9 of Steve Krug's <em>Don't Make Me Think.<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/user-tests#user-content-fn-1-95b35a" id="user-content-fnref-1-95b35a" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/space-33fee8c7cae9f2ac0518388871fd2445.jpeg" title="Leave a space stock image" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Leave some space</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Space</strong> is necessary for your participants to provide good feedback
during a user test. It's always tempting for me to ask railroading and leading questions. I tend to ask users and stakeholders
which of two options they prefer rather than finding out what they want. However, giving the space necessary to give
feedback on what a user actually wants or dislikes will lead to much more productive user testing. It's important
to ask more general questions that allow users to explore and express their own thoughts.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;This is a lesson that's useful in many aspects of a software development career. While
we're applying it here to UI and usability, leaving space for feedback and organic responses can also be extremely
helpful in requirements elicitation or just general discussions with coworkers.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/user-tests#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-95b35a">
<p>Krug, Steve. Don't Make Me Think: Revisited. A Common Sense Approach to Web and Mobile Usability. New Riders, 2014. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/user-tests#user-content-fnref-1-95b35a" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Focused Feedback]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/feedback</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/feedback"/>
        <updated>2024-10-18T17:45:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is a reflection of "How to Give Designers Feedback They Can Actually Use."]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is a reflection of "How to Give Designers Feedback They Can Actually Use."<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/feedback#user-content-fn-1-953c26" id="user-content-fnref-1-953c26" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/focus-864916a94fc7107c9ca2c65a751054ae.jpeg" title="Stay focused stock image" width="4501" height="3000" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Focus</strong> is the word that stands out to me from the article. Both giving &amp; receiving feedback
are based heavily on where you place your focus. When giving negative feedback, it's important to focus on what's wrong and what can be
improved rather than broad statements about quality or shortcomings of the designer. Giving direct, actionable feedback on how to improve
the product helps prevent the developer from feeling like the feedback is a criticism of themself.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;As a designer receiving negative feedback, it's also important to focus on that which you can take action on.
Getting caught up in the negativity of the feedback will only hinder your ability to improve and grow. You need to learn to take feedback as
a criticism of the work itself rather than of your own abilities. Even if the feedback isn't the most tactful, it's best to filter it down to
what you need to improve for your own sake.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Personally, I'm fairly aware of the fact that I take feedback to heart too much as a criticism of myself. It
can be hard to remember that most people just want to see the product in its best state, so I need to remember not to take it too hard in my
career.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/feedback#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-953c26">
<p>"How to Give Designers Feedback They Can Actually Use." Inside Design Blog, <a href="http://www.invisionapp.com/inside-design/give-designers-feedback/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.invisionapp.com/inside-design/give-designers-feedback/</a>. Accessed 16 Oct. 2024. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/feedback#user-content-fnref-1-953c26" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimalism in Portfolios]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/portfolios</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/portfolios"/>
        <updated>2024-10-16T06:12:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is a reflection of "31 Inspiring UX Portfolio Examples - with a Great Guide for Creating Yours."]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is a reflection of "31 Inspiring UX Portfolio Examples - with a Great Guide for Creating Yours."<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/portfolios#user-content-fn-1-1cb3a9" id="user-content-fnref-1-1cb3a9" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/minimalism-a361d22fbde3e919b2da3016e15630d1.jpeg" title="Minimalism stock image" width="4256" height="2832" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">A minimalist workstation</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>Minimalism</strong> is the key takeaway from this article. There are many adjacent concepts analyzed
and put forward to improve your UI/UX portfolio, but many of them also boil down to minimalism. Good portfolios use simple color schemes,
sleek buttons, and minimal text. These factors help catch the eyes of managers and guide them to the important ares of your portfolio.
Busier portfolios can distract from the work within them.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;This article was an important reminder not to over-design the simple things in this portfolio. By sticking
with minimal flare and a focus on the important elements, I hope to keep this portfolio more digestable for anyone digging into it.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/portfolios#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-1cb3a9">
<p>Klaudia Simon, Akos Izsak. "31 Inspiring UX Portfolio Examples - with a Great Guide for Creating Yours." UXfolio Blog, 8 Oct. 2024, blog.uxfol.io/ux-portfolio-examples/. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/portfolios#user-content-fnref-1-1cb3a9" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Navigation Concept Map]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/navigation</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/navigation"/>
        <updated>2024-10-10T10:15:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is a reflection of chapter 6 of Steve Krug's Don't Make Me Think]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is a reflection of chapter 6 of Steve Krug's <em>Don't Make Me Think<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/navigation#user-content-fn-1-244587" id="user-content-fnref-1-244587" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em>
containing a map of the key elements of strong navigation.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/nav_concept_map-88e08c422a892283e1e1e785f9b5f27d.jpg" title="Navigation stock image" width="1200" height="1344" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">My Concept Map</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Above, I've mapped my own hierarchy of important elements to UI navigation.
I consider the navbar to contain the most important elements while body is loosely more important than the
footer. From there, items are listed in order of importance for their sections. I'll explain a bit more
of my reasoning below.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;I put search at the top of the hierarchy since many users default to search before
attempting to muddle through any links as mentioned in <em>Don't Make Me Think.<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/navigation#user-content-fn-1-244587" id="user-content-fnref-1-244587-2" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em> Not having a good search can alienate a ton of users
who are expecting to use it exclusively. From there, I essentially ordered all the other link types based on how frequently they
should be used and what value they bring to the UI. External links are much lower than the rest because they take users
away from your UI, but they still may be necessary at times. Otherwise, links that lead to larger sections of the UI are
generally ranked higher than one-off pages in my eyes.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Though navigation is a key part of every UI, it feels like a concept which can fall to the
wayside when getting down into the details of implementing a new feature. This hierarchy will be a helpful guideline in
my career as a reminder of which elements are most important to focus on so as not to forget them when working in other
areas.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/navigation#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-244587">
<p>Krug, Steve. Don't Make Me Think: Revisited. A Common Sense Approach to Web and Mobile Usability. New Riders, 2014. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/navigation#user-content-fnref-1-244587" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a> <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/navigation#user-content-fnref-1-244587-2" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1-2" class="data-footnote-backref">↩<sup>2</sup></a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="ConceptMap" term="ConceptMap"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finding Inspiration]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/finding-inspiration</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/finding-inspiration"/>
        <updated>2024-10-03T17:03:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post covers an exercise I performed in which I found an art piece from a museum]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post covers an exercise I performed in which I found an art piece from a museum
to use as inspiration for creating a UI sketch.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/inspiration-f1b1e66b05830d9632f0e051c8c9ebc7.jpeg" title="Inspiration stock image" width="7189" height="4798" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Inspiration can be a tough thing to find at times. UI design is supposed to involve
artistic expression, so taking inspiration from traditional art may help design something you feel strongly about.
As such, I've went out to find an art piece to take cues from in a UI sketch of my own.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;For this activity, I chose a piece from the Sheldon Art Museum on the University of Nebraska - Lincoln
campus. This piece came from an artist known as Julius Schmidt from Stamford, Connecticut. The piece unfortunately is only labeled
as "Untitled Relief," but this should be enough to find it for yourself if you'd like. The piece is a cast iron sculpture with little
notion of any overarching ideas. Rather, it has many cut-outs with all kinds of intricate designs. In the following sections, I'll be
analyzing three of my favorite aspects of the piece.</p>
<strong>Labyrinthian</strong>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;While not all sections of the design have open routes to each other, the overall design reminds me of a
labyrinth or maze-like structure. Due to the ties of labyrinths to ancient cultures such as Egypt, Greece, &amp; Crete,<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/finding-inspiration#user-content-fn-1-a54404" id="user-content-fnref-1-a54404" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup> this brought me back
to reading books about Greek mythology as a child. I've always found the subject interesting, so attempting to build a UI that ties into
mythology seems like fun. Though labyrinthian design is in some ways antithetical to UI design (UIs should be simple, not eternally confusing),
I think a maze could make for a good logo.</p>
<strong>Archaic</strong>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;This may be a bit of a stretch as the piece was actually created in the 1960s, but I find that it resembles something
you would see at a historic site of an ancient city. As a cast iron piece stored outside, it is now rusty and archaic looking. Again, I've chosen an
aspect that should probably be avoided in UI design since it shouldn't feel dated, but I think I can continue to tie this in with the theme of
Greek mythology. Though not often thought about this way due to the lack of printing, fonts were used in many ancient civilizations for consistency in
labeling,<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/finding-inspiration#user-content-fn-2-a54404" id="user-content-fnref-2-a54404" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">2</a></sup> so I think using a primitive Greek-esque font in stylized aspects of the page could further connect to the mythology theme.</p>
<strong>Lack of Negative Space</strong>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;In yet another aspect that probably isn't suitable for UI design, I quite like the lack of negative space in this
sculpture. Almost everything about it is highly-designed and busy. Despite thinking this is great for a piece that feels like a labyrinth, it
stands out as something I should approach in the opposite manner for a UI design. I'm not sure if there's a term for what I'm thinking of as
negative inspiration in this sense, but it leads me to want to keep my composition simple. Negative space is a powerful tool for exactly that.<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/finding-inspiration#user-content-fn-3-a54404" id="user-content-fnref-3-a54404" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">3</a></sup></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;With those aspects of inspiration laid out, below is my UI sketch for a mobile app catalog of Greek mythology stories and books.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/greek_ui-056ac1c5a9a9fc30e93ad82f1e4a3300.jpg" title="A UI sketch of a mobile catalog for Greek mythology" width="3000" height="3102" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Mobile Mythology Catalog</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;This app would be similar to something like Libby or Kindle where you can search for new works to read, save them to
a reading list, and read the work from directly within the app. Though I tried to make the styling feel ancient Greece themed with headers and icons,
I would keep longer strings of text to a more standard font to make them easier to read. I decided to also go with a maze for the logo to match
the labyrinth inspiration. Had I iterated on this more, I think the maze should have a more distinct pattern to it rather than a generic maze. It fits
the theme less, but I think it would help the logo stick better in the minds of users.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;I'm not sure if I fully succeeded in using negative space here
since the app seems a little packed, but it's hard not to use all the space you're given when designing a mobile app. There's some amount of space between
cards on the carousels which is probably the most significant use of negative space here.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;In conclusion, I'm pretty satisfied with the result of this exercise. I've found that inspiration from traditional sources
can be interpreted in unconventional manners to create something that still follows good design principles. When looking for a place to start on
something new, perhaps an underrated place to look is at something old.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/finding-inspiration#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-a54404">
<p>Callaway, Linda. "The Symbolism of Labyrinths: A Journey through Mystery and Meaning." Symbol Genie, 25 Aug. 2023, <a href="http://www.symbolgenie.com/symbolism-of-labyrinths/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.symbolgenie.com/symbolism-of-labyrinths/</a>. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/finding-inspiration#user-content-fnref-1-a54404" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-2-a54404">
<p>Fontfabric. "History and Evolution of Typography - Extended." Fontfabric, 20 Oct. 2023, <a href="http://www.fontfabric.com/blog/history-and-evolution-of-typography-fonts-timeline/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.fontfabric.com/blog/history-and-evolution-of-typography-fonts-timeline/</a>. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/finding-inspiration#user-content-fnref-2-a54404" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 2" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-3-a54404">
<p>DeGuzman, Kyle. "How to Use Negative Space in Composition." StudioBinder, 31 Jan. 2023, <a href="http://www.studiobinder.com/blog/what-is-negative-space-definition/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.studiobinder.com/blog/what-is-negative-space-definition/</a>. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/finding-inspiration#user-content-fnref-3-a54404" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 3" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="FreeForm" term="FreeForm"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Different Colors Can Change a UI's Mood]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-3</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-3"/>
        <updated>2024-09-26T21:29:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post contains a few recreations of a login screen for one of my Ubuntu virtual machines.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post contains a few recreations of a login screen for one of my Ubuntu virtual machines.
The theme I use can be found here: <a href="https://www.gnome-look.org/p/1267246/" target="_blank">Gnome-Look: Nordic Theme</a>.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/UICrop-2bface7b733039280d334e9781773222.png" title="An Ubuntu login screen" width="1108" height="756" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">My VM's Login Screen</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;The color scheme used for this theme could possibly be described as analogous since it's based on dark blues and blue greens.
However, I think monochrome or perhaps even monotone (with the exception of the blue green highlights) is a better description of the theme depending if you
view these as shades of blue or gray.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Regardless, these colors are meant to be easy on the eye. I feel that it's meant to create a calming mood for something that
you use regularly rather than being a vibrant or eye-catching design. That's not to say it isn't interesting as I think the colors here play off of each
other perfectly. More information on the Nord theme can be found <a href="https://github.com/nordtheme/nord" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;As an exercise, I've attempted to recreate this login screen (minus the mountains in the background as that would be a nightmare) in
three varying color combinations to see the effect this has on the interface's mood. Below is the original mockup with the same color scheme.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/mockup-85a1752fa34e8175db098e077ff545af.png" title="A recreated Ubuntu login screen" width="1035" height="576" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Original Mockup</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;First is a recreation of this design into something that pops off the screen much more. Instead of the Nord theme, I've went for something
closer to a cyberpunk aesthetic.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/cyberpunk_mockup-443f9b7aa23e7df98f0ff8e029c9f74e.png" title="A recreated Ubuntu login screen with cyberpunk colors" width="1035" height="576" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Cyberpunk Mockup</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;This color scheme obviously throws all the subtlety and ease of use out the window. Cyberpunk designs are meant to grab your attention
from anything else due to the vibrant, somewhat clashy colors. I would say this is closest to an adventurous analogous color combination based on the blues
and bright purple/pink with the addition of the yellow which doesn't fit that theme. In reality, I'm not sure it matches any of the harmonious palettes of color theory.
However, someone looking for a futuristic theme that pops may love a more refined version of this theme.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Next up, I've stuck with the modern/futuristic idea but switched over to a more minimalist palette of red and black.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/redline_mockup-8628e8c6ad690c4e24476cb8ae85172d.png" title="A recreated Ubuntu login screen with minimalistic black and red colors" width="1035" height="576" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Sleek Minimalist Mockup</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;This scheme returns to something much easier on the eye but in a less subdued way than the original theme. This is meant to feel modern if
not futuristic with the bold red accents. This has none of the natural edge of the orignal. Again, this doesn't really fit into one of the harmonious palettes since we're
only using one non-neutral color. However, it's still a great design for someone who wants some edge in their UI without sacrificing usability or inducing eye strain.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Lastly, I'm intentionally picking a harmonious color palette of triads. For this, I've picked the primary colors to aim for something
more childlike.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/childlike_mockup-33c356e2d8b2bc6b3279bb5ab4c19f51.png" title="A recreated Ubuntu login screen with childlike colors" width="1035" height="576" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Childlike Mockup</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;This final mockup is closer to the cyberpunk aesthetic in the sense that it uses multiple strong colors which fight for your attention. It again
lacks all of the subtlety of the minimalist and original designs, and it definitely has no roots in nature. As I've worded it already, it comes off as childlike as you would
expect to see these colors on toys or one of those tables/rugs with a top-down view of a city that kids love to play on. If for some unholy reason you decide
that your 6-year old needs to learn Linux, this UI is perfect for you. For anyone else, I can't really see this being a popular choice.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;To wrap this up, I'd like to reflect on which of these color palettes I find most effective for a login screen. By effective, I'm talking about
which one uses colors that play off of each other in the best ways. This would also be the design I expect to be most popular were you to offer it on a theme store.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;I'm just going to get it out of the way that I think the original theme blows anything I made out of the water. Nord is a well-established
color palette created by talented designers for something perfectly usable. It's grounded in nature, and I love dark, calming themes when it comes to something I want to use
every day. They've obviously put much more effort into fine tuning the color choices to make sure everything works together.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;However, if I were to pick the most effective of my own color palettes, I really like how the red and black theme turned out for similar
reasons that I like Nord. It's simple and something that I could look at during any time of the day. The cyberpunk and childlike aesthetics have their use cases as well,
but I feel that they would be too much for me if I were coming to my PC early in the morning or late at night. They're too aggressive and bold for something I want to
use regularly. I think the red and black strikes a good balance between ease of use and boldness in the red accents.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;In conclusion, this exercise has helped me better understand how color palettes can completely change the mood of a UI despite none of the
elements changing. This is important to remember as a designer since we always want to make sure we're choosing colors intentionally. Color combinations should always
complement the use cases of interfaces instead of just being chosen haphazardly.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="FreeForm" term="FreeForm"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Did I Choose Purple For My Portfolio?]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-2</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-2"/>
        <updated>2024-09-25T18:50:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following blog post explains my reasoning based on Eiseman's The Complete Color Harmony for choosing purple as the primary color of this portfolio.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following blog post explains my reasoning based on Eiseman's <em>The Complete Color Harmony<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-2#user-content-fn-1-ccc164" id="user-content-fnref-1-ccc164" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em> for choosing purple as the primary color of this portfolio.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/purple-be7f6d2de53bf8057d7b122c004b7674.jpeg" title="A sunset over a purple sky" width="5000" height="3333" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">In the Simplest Terms: Purple is Stunning</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;While I won't deny that purple being my favorite color plays a large role in the decision to use it here,
there are further reasons why I think it's a good choice for a UI (though to some degree, I'm justifying this for the same reasons it's my favorite color).</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;I find purple unique in the sense that you don't see it used often in more professional settings. It's often relegated to its connotations of royalty, mystique,
or flamboyancy, but I personally agree with the sentiment that purples on the blue end of the spectrum can appear very elegant &amp; dignified. It's eye-catching
but in a subtler sense than a bright orange or deep red. Purple makes a statement without screaming at you to listen.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Speaking to those who choose to listen is how I like to view my own approach to conversation. I don't take my place in a conversation
by being the loudest but simply by having something to say. Sometimes this may get drowned out by louder voices such as the oranges &amp; reds of the world, but
the reserved thoughts are there for those who choose to listen. Perhaps this has nothing to do with purple, and I'm just projecting my personality onto
my favorite color. Perhaps my personality lead me to choose a color I identify with.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Or, perhaps purple has influenced my personality... much like the personality of this portfolio.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-2#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-ccc164">
<p>Eiseman, Leatrice. The Complete Color Harmony: Expert Color Information for Professional Results. Rockport Publishers, an Imprint of The Quarto Group, 2017. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-2#user-content-fnref-1-ccc164" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="FreeForm" term="FreeForm"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Color is to Design as Spice is to Cooking]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-1</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-1"/>
        <updated>2024-09-23T16:23:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following post reflects on Eiseman's The Complete Color Harmony as it relates to color theory and the role of color in design as compared to spice in cooking.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following post reflects on Eiseman's <em>The Complete Color Harmony<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-1#user-content-fn-1-6bf4cc" id="user-content-fnref-1-6bf4cc" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em> as it relates to color theory and the role of color in design as compared to spice in cooking.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/spice-2ab3b9d8248ecff59fc2f880fe7ef236.jpeg" title="Various colorful spices in bowls" width="5849" height="3910" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Spice Itself Comes in Many Colors</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;In the same sense that no dish is complete without spice, no interface is complete without color. Sure, some people cook with
little more than salt in the same way that some websites use simple black text on white backgrounds. Though there may be a time and place for this type of
design (Wikipedia comes to mind, but even they use some amount of color), most interfaces would be horribly boring without a good color scheme. In the same
way, salt may be all you need when cooking for picky eaters or just making something edible, but the dish will never reach the same heights it would with
a full flavor profile of spices.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Color doesn't often define an interface, but it's an almost necessary component to create something that will stick with users
after they stop interacting with your interface due to the emotional significance of color. Like spice, it's also important to pick the correct color combinations.
Throwing everything &amp; the kitchen sink into a dish or design is a good way to overwhelm users and create something with no identity. Color palettes are often created
from three colors which play off of each other in one way or another just like a recipe often calls for a handful of complementary spices.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Color's importance and necessitation of both restraint and combination are important to remember for anyone going into UI design
or really any career that relates to interfaces. Without understanding these concepts, you're bound to go too far to one end of the spectrum. Understanding
how to use smart color combinations and experiment to create your own unique themes will elevate everything from new UIs to simple updates of existing ones.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-1#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-6bf4cc">
<p>Eiseman, Leatrice. The Complete Color Harmony: Expert Color Information for Professional Results. Rockport Publishers, an Imprint of The Quarto Group, 2017. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/colors-1#user-content-fnref-1-6bf4cc" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="ApproximateAnalogy" term="ApproximateAnalogy"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aesthetic Design - How to Design Effective Slides]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/aesthetic-design</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/aesthetic-design"/>
        <updated>2024-09-18T19:49:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following tutorial contains key points & reminders from Presentation Zen on how to create attention-grabbing/effective PowerPoint slides.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following tutorial contains key points &amp; reminders from <em>Presentation Zen<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/aesthetic-design#user-content-fn-1-ec306f" id="user-content-fnref-1-ec306f" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em> on how to create attention-grabbing/effective PowerPoint slides.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/presentation_stock-b8059233ce7b2e3dabee2892be754d00.jpeg" title="Example presentations with good formatting" width="5477" height="2739" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">An Example of Simple But Effective Slides</p><p></p>
<p>Avoid Bullet-Points (mostly)</p>
<ul>
<li>Bullet-points are often used as a crutch in slide design with most of the words to be spoken, but they should be used sparingly.</li>
<li>You can get away with including much less of what you're going to say on the slides, or you can break up lists into multiple slides with one or two key points each.</li>
</ul>
<p>Pay Attention to Eyes</p>
<ul>
<li>When including images of people or animals, make sure the eyes don't lead users away from slide content.</li>
<li>Try to use images where the eyes point at your content, and flip/rearrange images that don't.</li>
</ul>
<p>Break Up Large Quotes (if necessary)</p>
<ul>
<li>Longer quotes can be easier to read in chunks instead of a one large block.</li>
<li>If doing this, break it down into distinct sections on different slides &amp; focus in on the significance of each one.</li>
</ul>
<p>Eliminate Noise Around Charts</p>
<ul>
<li>Make sure background colors &amp; images don't conflict with the viewer's ability to read a read any elements of charts.</li>
<li>Select simple graph layouts (2D is almost always better than 3D).</li>
<li>Choose colors for graph elements that work well together &amp; don't distract from information.</li>
</ul>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/aesthetic-design#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-ec306f">
<p>Reynolds, Garr. Presentation Zen: Simple Ideas on Presentation Design and Delivery. Pearson Education, 2019. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/aesthetic-design#user-content-fnref-1-ec306f" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="Tutorial" term="Tutorial"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Design Rules - Conciseness]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/design-rules</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/design-rules"/>
        <updated>2024-09-13T20:48:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is a reflection of chapters 2-5 of Steve Krug's Don't Make Me Think.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is a reflection of chapters 2-5 of Steve Krug's <em>Don't Make Me Think.<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/design-rules#user-content-fn-1-4fbcb4" id="user-content-fnref-1-4fbcb4" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/brevity-2780cf0257dc8e2a1b598c9ef7aa280d.jpeg" title="A stock image stating &amp;#39;less is more&amp;#39;" width="6316" height="3744" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">To quote Shakespeare, "Brevity is the soul of wit"</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Much of Krug's advice seems to revolve around a focus on brevity &amp; conciseness.
Too many words will bog down a UI &amp; cause the reader to skim too hard leading to them missing the info that's actually important.
Keeping text to a minimum of just the important lines helps catch users' eyes with only what is necessary to digest the page
&amp; reach their goals. This point feels especially important for me to keep in mind in my career as I often have trouble with
brevity in general. Even in my personal life, I can't help but over-explain things, so I always send the "essay" texts that everyone hates.
Knowing when brevity is important is very helpful to me so that I can focus on it to try to counteract my instincts or cut down what
I've already written.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/design-rules#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-4fbcb4">
<p>Krug, Steve. Don't Make Me Think: Revisited. A Common Sense Approach to Web and Mobile Usability. New Riders, 2014. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/design-rules#user-content-fnref-1-4fbcb4" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Analysis of Shneiderman - The Eyes Have It]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/shneiderman-analysis</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/shneiderman-analysis"/>
        <updated>2024-09-06T15:06:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is a meta reflection on Ben Shneiderman's paper, "The Eyes Have It: A Task by Data Type Taxonomy for Information Visualizations" as well as a reflection on the importance of this paper's concepts in the industry.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is a meta reflection on Ben Shneiderman's paper, "The Eyes Have It: A Task by Data Type Taxonomy for Information Visualizations"<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/shneiderman-analysis#user-content-fn-1-5da721" id="user-content-fnref-1-5da721" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup> as well as a reflection on the importance of this paper's concepts in the industry.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/tunnel_vision-565df1a7f50d952add711ac357c6eac8.jpeg" title="Tunnel vision" width="5856" height="3904" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Artistic Depiction of Tunnel Vision</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;I found a lot of this paper to be bogged down in implementation details of specific problems/solutions which I don't find terribly helpful when trying to learn a concept.
It's okay to provide examples, but the section on "Overview" for example felt overly-specific. I don't see as much value in talking about specific zoom factors and field-of-view boxes when introducing a concept in a paper like this.
I would've preferred more high-level explanation &amp; justification for the techniques personally.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;As far as career importance, the meta point would be to avoid getting caught up in implementation details when having conversations with non-technical stakeholders (or even technical stakeholders in certain cases).
In terms of the actual content of the reading, the principles themselves that were outlined are important to keep in mind while building a UI as they're good guidelines &amp; standards for guiding a user's interaction with your interface.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/shneiderman-analysis#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-5da721">
<p>B. Shneiderman, "The eyes have it: a task by data type taxonomy for information visualizations," Proceedings 1996 IEEE Symposium on Visual Languages, Boulder, CO, USA, 1996, pp. 336-343, doi: 10.1109/VL.1996.545307. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/shneiderman-analysis#user-content-fnref-1-5da721" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="WordJournal" term="WordJournal"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conceptual Models are to Design as Song Lyrics are to Music]]></title>
        <id>https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/conceptual-models</id>
        <link href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/conceptual-models"/>
        <updated>2024-08-28T18:29:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post is a reflection of chapter 1 of Don Norman's The Design of Everyday Things.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is a reflection of chapter 1 of Don Norman's <em>The Design of Everyday Things.<sup><a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/conceptual-models#user-content-fn-1-df3995" id="user-content-fnref-1-df3995" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Alt text" src="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/assets/images/lyrics-81bfa96009080cf81d01e48ef3ee08ef.jpeg" title="A stock image of random song lyrics" width="5472" height="3648" class="img_ev3q">
</p><p style="text-align:center">Both lyrics and conceptual models have infinite interpretations</p><p></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Most songs have lyrics written with a level of depth &amp; hidden meaning that their
original intent is only fully understood by their writers. As the rest of us hear these songs, we piece together
the lyrics into a story or message which we probably perceive as the intended one. We may not have even heard the correct
words in certain portions (this happens to me all the time) but manage to craft an understanding of the lyrics which we find coherent.
In some cases, we may even search out what insight the artist has given on a song and realize that our perception wasn't nearly as
accurate as we realized. These concepts all have parallels in conceptual models such as forming a mental model from experimentation
with affordances or interpreting signifiers, misinterpreting signifiers to mean something unintended, and consulting resources from
the designers to try to understand their conceptual model.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;For me, tying these concepts to something I've experienced often in everyday life is
a useful way to remember how wildly conceptual models can vary from person to person. This should be useful in my
career as it's a reminder to design interfaces with signifiers that are as unambiguous as possible to try to
transfer as much of my conceptual model to the user as possible.</p>
<!-- -->
<section data-footnotes="true" class="footnotes"><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7 sr-only" id="footnote-label">Footnotes<a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/conceptual-models#footnote-label" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Footnotes" title="Direct link to Footnotes">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1-df3995">
<p>Norman, Don. The Design of Everyday Things. Basic Books, 2013. <a href="https://jnichols12.github.io/jake-ui-portfolio/blog/conceptual-models#user-content-fnref-1-df3995" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1" class="data-footnote-backref">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Jake Nichols</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jnichols12</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="ApproximateAnalogy" term="ApproximateAnalogy"/>
    </entry>
</feed>